this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
PC radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society software Magazine
online at computer.org software
for software engineering radio this is
Robert blumen
I have with me today two guests Donald
Fisher who is the co-founder and CEO of
tidelift he's a board member of several
companies and organizations and is a
graduate of Stanford University where he
received his Ms in computer science
Donald welcome to software engineering
radio thank you very glad to be here
Donald would you like to say anything
else about your background yeah I think
you encapsulated pretty well you know
I've been fascinated by software in
particular open source software and the
creators and communities behind it for
most of my career and excited to talk
about some of that here with you today
my second guest is Jordan harband Jordan
is an open source maintainer at large
he's contributed to the JavaScript
specification he is a member of the
openjs foundations cross project Council
and he has formerly developer relations
engineer at coinbase Jordan welcome to
software engineering radio thank you
happy to be here would you like to
expand on your background at all no I
think you've covered it pretty well
thank you let's proceed to the content
we will be talking today about securing
the software supply chain this episode
goes very well with 535 which was about
software supply chain attacks but it did
not offer Solutions today we'll be
looking more at Solutions Donald briefly
could you tell us when we're talking
about supply chain and keep in mind we
had a whole episode in this but a quick
review of what do we mean by software
supply chain yeah absolutely so the
so-called software supply chain is
really anything that affects your
software at any point in its development
and release including you know the
original creation writing the software
continuous integration continuous
deployment pipeline that it goes through
all of the channels through which your
software flows from the moment of
creation into production and you know
that includes a whole bunch of of
different systems and sources of
software in particular one of the areas
that's been in the spotlight quite a bit
recently is third-party open source
software which is you know one of the
key ingredients that goes into most
applications these days
we did as I mentioned cover a lot of
attacks on the supply chain in 535 it
became clear that supply chain attacks
are not any particular type of attack
like say buffer overflow or escalation
of privilege they could be any type of
attack whatever that attacks and
component of the supply chain how can we
talk about securing the supply chain
when it's not any particular type of
attack that we're defending Jordan yeah
I think in the same way as every time
you add people to your company you're
incurring some trade-offs you have more
eyes on your code base you have more
people who can test it more people who
can make sure it's of good quality you
also have more people that could make
mistakes that could get a laptop stolen
at a coffee shop that could fall on hard
times and get bribed to betray the
company in some way you also have more
potential people who could be enemy
State actors right that happened at
Twitter on one or two occasions but
these are all trade-offs as you add more
people right and it's the same with
adding dependencies to your supply chain
each dependency is one or more people
who maintain that dependency and there
are huge benefits to adding them in
terms of there's more eyes on the
software there's more experience
involved you have more specialists
who can do that the specific task
they're charged with doing exceedingly
well you also have more points of
failure and I think that securing your
supply chain is really a balancing act
about how you accept the large benefits
of adding people to your process while
still managing the weakest link in any
process on the planet the humans
well I was researching this interview I
came across a quote from Beau Woods of
the cyber security and infrastructure
Security Agency
he says that software supply chain
issues are more organizational than
technological does either of you agree
or disagree with bow Woods on that I
think the people part and the technology
part are co-equal in this question right
it's really both people and technology
that play a role here and it's actually
true not just on the consumption side of
software the software developers that
are assembling existing code and
authoring new code to comprise a
application for a business purpose it's
also true on the creation side of the
components that flow into those
applications right there are I mean
often left underappreciated including
recently is that there's humans Behind
These open source projects that we rely
on and so we can't just solve all of the
problems by throwing more technology and
software and tools at it there's also a
human element a people process and also
a human incentivization and Alignment
challenge that we need to Grapple with
Jordan do you have anything to add to
that yeah I I totally agree with that
sentiment I think that my comments would
be easily interpreted as saying that
it's only the humans that you have to be
concerned about and I think I was adding
a little hyperbole because it I think
it's primarily the humans that are under
addressed and that needs to be sort of
compensated for by overdoing it in the
other direction but obviously you cannot
ignore the moving parts of the
technology involved I think that it
takes a lot of effort to consider both
of those things and handle them you know
invest in them appropriately and have
the appropriate checks and balances on
both sides of those things yeah I think
that's a challenge ahead of us all how
to balance those Jordan suppose you are
looking at organization they tell you
we've set up Jenkins build server we're
running a bunch of builds we haven't
really thought about security do you
have a checklist or where to start what
does that organization need to do to
improve their situation
your question omits a lot of information
I would need so I would want to
understand the entire process that leads
to code arriving in that build server so
I would want to understand who has
permissions to do what who has to review
it what are the gating procedures to
make sure the code has moved through
this pipeline appropriately what are the
remediation paths if problems are
discovered at any point in the pipeline
like can it be rolled back do you file a
ticket who do you notify and once that
is all kind of in order then you get to
the build system and then your question
is well if somebody were to compromise
the build system what could they do and
ideally the only thing they could do is
make perhaps make Network requests and
perhaps build a corrupted or malicious
artifact to deploy and so then the next
question would be those same sort of
kind of chain of custody and permissions
questions around the build environment
who has the ability to configure that
and verify it and how do you make sure
that code that comes in even though
ideally it's trusted how do you make
sure that that code cannot exploit any
vulnerabilities in the build environment
and to produce those harmful Network
requests or file system access and so on
so we've been talking at a pretty high
level I'd like to drill down more into
some particulars starting with the role
of Open Source it's pretty much
impossible now to do anything without
probably pulling in hundreds of Open
Source libraries is open source a major
Vector for supply chain attacks
so it's a vector for software supply
chain attacks for sure now open source
software is still just software right so
you know it's going to suffer from a lot
of the challenges that any software
including you know privately proprietary
software would face in terms of secure
development and secure release and
secure handling and in fact in a lot of
ways open source software has some
advantages over privately built software
I mean there's inherently the many eyes
principle you know many eyes will find
even obscure bugs it's been said there's
inherently more transparency around open
source than your garden variety internal
proprietary software project but I think
the balance there is that because open
source in particular these popular
Frameworks and components that are so
often used in our applications because
they're so widely used the blast radius
of an incident can be really vast I mean
we're talking about frequently about
open source packages that are downloaded
and incorporated into application builds
billions of times a month right so one
of those packages being compromised in a
supply chain attack can have really
really far-reaching implications and I
think that's why a lot of the
conversation around software supply
chain security has recently focused on
this part of it the open source software
supply chain security challenge
yeah I would add in the same way that a
security attack can compromise things a
bug can cause problems too right and if
I just work at one company the
likelihood is that my bug is that if I
make a mistake I'm probably just going
to break that website let's say it's a
web company but as we've seen with AWS
for example when AWS goes down a lot of
websites go down you know when you have
a shared piece of infrastructure and
that shared piece has problems you see
the impact of those problems spread much
more widely and so it's the same with
open source is that the type of innocent
bug that one can commit can have a much
wider effect than one can expect one
time I refactored a package and changed
the text of an error message to make it
better to make it more helpful and I had
no idea that some very popular packages
were using the text of that error
message and like in their code paths and
so I broke angular and Ember users all
over the planet by changing the text of
an error message luckily I was able to
find it and fix it within like a matter
of hours but you know that wasn't an
attack that was just a mistake and it
still caused like widespread damage so I
would say that in the same way that
Donald phrase it as its a vector I think
when anyone says something is a major
Vector are you talking about the scale
of its reach or are you talking about it
having outsized risk more than it quote
should and I would say that because open
source is used so widely across many
different Industries and companies and
code bases it is a major Vector in terms
of scale whether it's an outsized vector
or not I don't believe it to be but
obviously that part would be debatable
in calling it major you can In fairness
say that's a vague term and let me try
to describe a little more of what I was
thinking which is when you run a package
manager it pulls in packages that you
know about but you didn't write them and
you probably haven't done a thorough
audit those packages and then it pulls
in a ton of other dependencies Which
pull in other dependencies by the time
you're done you may have hundreds or
thousands of packages if you looked at
the list of all the dependencies there
probably some of you don't even know why
they're there nor did you write them and
I'm not sure it's the case that it's you
can control everything that happens
within your own organization but you
certainly can't control everything that
happens outside of your organization so
you've imparted this enormous amount of
code you didn't write and that sounds
like there's some risk involved well and
I think you just nailed the problem
right is even within your own
organization especially as your
organization grows you can't even
control all the code written within it I
don't think you know the people
deploying facebook.com all of their
internal code that's used on it I am
quite sure that it is written by people
across the company who may not even work
there anymore and who knows how much how
audited all of it is and it's the same
for any company Google or IBM or
whatever I think that when you
acknowledge that you cannot ever
reliably audit all of your code whether
it's internal or external then it's the
fact that it's external no longer
differentiates anything and in fact then
you need to design your processes around
the reality that you cannot audit all of
your code instead of based on the fear
that you haven't and once you do that
then you've solved that problem for
internal or external code Donald think
you have something to add I would just
add to what Jordan said there that
certainly is not possible for every
organization to audit every line of
every bit of code that's written
continuously all of the time as
applications are being assembled however
there are you know well-known
well-established principles for secure
software development that can be used
internally in an organization for the
code that's written there and one of the
opportunities that's you know coming to
the Forefront in the res recent
conversations on the open source
software side is to establish what those
standards and processes should be for
third-party open source packages and
then provide both a way to communicate
that to the open source creators who we
rely on and verify that those practices
are being followed and really
importantly create an incentive there as
well or you know a recognition of the
work that's being done that we all get
to rely on so in a lot of ways that
taking some of the process and
standardization that's been designed for
software development within an
organization and extending that in a
useful way to these third-party
independently authored open source
projects as well I agree with your
Nuance so there was a thing floating
around the internet a few years ago
about how you should design your program
to crash meaning instead of trying to
make a program that never crashes you
should design one that at all times is
saving a state and that at all times can
be reopened and restore itself what I
like about this philosophy is that it's
accepting the reality that all programs
will crash and it is instead designing
processes around that reality to make it
so that a crash is not a big deal you
should reopen it and so similarly it's
not that code is unauditable it's that
you're never going to read every line of
code and so how do you design your
processes around that assuming that code
will be compromised assuming that there
will be bugs and secure processes
immutable package repositories public
databases of checkpoints and
attestations that have been made about
individual immutable packages are all
really wonderful ways that you can
design around the reality that every bit
of code no matter its source will
eventually have bugs or be a security
attack vector or you might be going with
that Jordan is there's a well-known
security concept called defense in depth
which is the idea of having multiple
layers of security an example would be
if someone gets into your network but
they don't have root on all your
machines if they get onto one of your
machines they don't have credentials for
all the databases and so on so the
entire system should not be compromised
if one layer fails is that more or less
where you're going with that observation
yeah I think so it's I've also heard
that described as moat based security
where you have a ring of moats and it
doesn't you know each one that they get
in doesn't give them the entire Castle
it just gives them a slightly different
advantage so there are a couple
directions we could go with this
discussion of auditing and how do you
manage as large amounts of code that you
didn't write one of them is scanning and
I do want to talk about that but right
about now we've been talking about open
source I want to cover there are some
efforts going on in the community by
organizations such as the Linux
foundation and open source software
Foundation to improve the overall
security profile of Open Source software
is either of you familiar with any of
those efforts Donald
yeah in fact I think we both had some
engagement around some of those efforts
so you know you mentioned the open
source security Foundation or openssf
that's a industry collaboration where
tidelift my company has been one of the
participating entities that gathered to
work on some of these challenges and
openssf has had some really useful kind
of umbrella of projects some that were
pre-existing and sort of adopted into
the effort some of which are novel one
that in particular I think has been
really helpful in this conversation is
the openssf security scorecards project
so what security scorecards is about is
essentially agreeing on what are some of
these practices that we would all like
our software the creation of our
software to adhere to right whether it's
security of the systems that are being
used to host the code or to package the
code or whether it's you know specific
secure coding practices that are being
taken or different kinds of preventative
analysis that can be undertaken around
open source code such as you know
fuzzing it or supplying it with random
inputs to find you know potential
Avenues of vulnerability so the security
scorecards project has been great
because it's been a way to sort of
catalog or inventory what's the wish
list of what we would like all of our
software to follow in particular open
source software projects and that's an
important part of the challenge is just
agreeing what our desired state would be
then I think some of the opportunity in
the industry is how can we cause that to
happen right how can we get the right
folks including companies and
organizations like the ones that are
predominantly authoring standards like
the openssf security scorecards are
contributing to them
but also the independent creators you
know folks like Jordan frankly who are
authoring a lot of those open source
projects outside of a traditional
corporate context we need to meet in the
middle there and convene these two
audiences if we're gonna turn it from
being just a wish list of attributes
that we wish software could have to a
list of attributes that we have
confidence or know that software has
because we've engaged with the actual
creators the industry could agree on
what these attributes are would there be
a standardized way for an open source
project to either get certified or to
advertise metadata saying I have been
fuzzed my code is on a secure server
code has been audited it has passed this
and this and this it could be read by
machines that would enable you to score
your own code base
yeah well the openssf security scorecard
project does include you know various
ways for some of the stacks to be
communicated in machine readable formats
but some of them require a human
attestation right around what's
happening and so you know that
attestation can be digitized but it
cannot necessarily be determined without
the involvement of the creators there
right and I think this is an important
point that gets to your defense and
depth argument earlier the traditional
approach in the industry has been very
much a downstream tools-based approach
it's been centered around different
software tools that we can apply against
either the code that's being written
inside an organization or the code that
we import packaged you know third-party
open source code that we import looking
for known vulnerabilities that have a
identifier
etc etc but there's only so much that a
downstream tool like that can do by
looking at just the code itself without
actually having a connection back to the
moment of creation the human or group of
humans who author that code and knows
all the surrounding context about you
know how that code came to be and what
standards and processes were being
followed do you have any thoughts on how
to incorporate that human context into
the broader supply chain
yeah so I mean this is one of the
challenges that we're working on at
tidelift is creating both a incentive
mechanism that makes it clear to those
independent maintainers that we you know
what we would ask of them and then
rather than just placing yet another
obligation on these folks who are
creating this code that we rely on in
our Enterprise and organizational
applications we're also providing a
economic incentive to go undertake this
non-trivial work to cause these
practices to be followed and to document
how they're being followed in these you
know combination of machine readable and
human validated mechanisms I think
Jordan probably could speak to this as
well yeah without speaking to the merits
of any particular system the world is
largely capitalism and thus the only you
know it's not a pure capitalism we have
regulation but that means that there's
really only two mechanisms to exert
leverage in the world
capital and the law and so if we want
something to happen like if we want open
source software to be more secure those
are the two mechanisms spend money put
money towards it and or regulate it and
provide incentives penalties to make
what we want happen and the way that the
tech industry has been treating open
source for decades has been essentially
as a source of free labor but they keep
wanting things from the open source
ecosystem we want you to make your
software secure we want you to fix bugs
we want you to release on a timely
fashion and so forth well inject Capital
that's where we're at if you don't like
that as a mechanism and you don't want
to lobby for regulation then vote for a
different economic system I mean
similarly to my earlier comments we need
to acknowledge the reality that we're in
the reality we're in is capitalism so
spend your Capital to make it happen so
any improvements we might talk about
Jordan at some point they involve
someone has to do them or they involve
resources like servers in compute time
your point is that those researchers
have to come from somewhere and the
people providing their time have other
things they could be doing yep and so if
there's funding to make these
improvements that would encourage them
to be done yeah and I mean the so I can
speak to myself personally as it relates
to tide lifts like at tidelift as a
funding source
so I am doing hopefully all the best
practices of software maintenance for
all of my packages and I'm doing that
largely out of a sense of ethics and
ideology however if at any point in the
future I decided those were no longer
enough for me that would suck for the
entire ecosystem that is depending on my
packages
the best way to make sure that those
incentives remain even if my mind
changes again is capital if I have a
source of income related to it then I'm
going to think a lot harder about
changing my mind on a whim about ethics
and morals and whatnot I think we can't
again acknowledging the reality we're in
at least in the U.S money is required
for health care for raising your
children for having a home for buying
food and these things are pretty
important so if you want to make sure
that something happens you tie those
things to that thing happening and money
is the the glue to tie them together so
I'm going to tie up this discussion
about open source and move on to
something different we have been
addressing this issue of how do you have
some understanding or risk mitigation of
large amounts of code that maybe you
wrote or maybe other people wrote it
there are different types of automated
scan that could be put into the pipeline
neither of you like to address the role
of automated detection in preventing
exploits from being injected into the
supply chain Donald
sure so definitely there is a role an
important role for different types of
application security software tools that
can scan for different kinds of
vulnerability patterns or known
vulnerabilities using different
approaches a couple different
subcategories of that class of tool or
product for example there's a long
established category of static software
analysis tools that look for the
structure of software programs and look
for you know coding patterns that can be
suggest of leaving open security
vulnerabilities there's a second class
of products that are commonly called the
dynamic scanning tools that more are
essentially running different kinds of
exploitation paths against whole
applications or parts of applications
often following you know Common exploit
paths like cross site scripting or
techniques like that and then there's a
the third category certainly pertaining
to open source software that's had a lot
of adoption in recent years the category
of software composition analysis the
tools that help you look at what are all
of the ingredients flowing into your
application and cross-checking those
against lists of known vulnerabilities
oftentimes drawn from the national
vulnerability database these security
vulnerabilities that people know from
their naming convention the cve
vulnerabilities and so all of those are
I think great tools they're well worn
and time established as part of your
defense in-depth approach but I think
that the moment now is demonstrating to
us that that's not the sum total of
everything that we could be doing around
software supply chain risk management
there are other things that we can do
you know one of the things that I think
personally I'm very fascinated by is how
we can add a layer of kind of
inadveranced upstream or proactive
engagement with the open source creators
behind our projects to agree in advance
what are some of these practices that we
would like to see followed and engage in
the process of creating and releasing
the software before it even flows into
our organization I saw that you know
recently echoed in the words of a senior
Bank executive who I saw speaking just
last week who said their philosophy at
this global bank is the best way to deal
with security vulnerabilities is to head
them off in the first place not just to
have the fastest scanner because if
you're relying just on reactive scanning
tools there's always going to be a
window of vulnerability no matter how
quickly you can go but if you can head
off the issue entirely using a
combination of some of these tools like
static analysis and dynamic analysis but
I think now importantly agreeing on the
practices that need to be followed
before that software flows into your
organization that's really the best
solution to find and what you're talking
about is the open source packages would
adopt not only scanners but other
security practices on their own and then
there'd be some way of communicating
that the project has adopted those
practices so you know that you're
pulling in only projects that have
adhered to a certain level of best
practices is that more or less what
you're talking about yeah and that
connects back to we were talking about
what are some of these lists of
standards that folks would like to have
their software adhere to like the open
ssf
security scorecards project but not only
that I mean there's also now
requirements coming not just from
industry but also from government so you
know Jordan talked a little bit about
the role of capital and law
law is showing up in this conversation
recently as well you know so for example
you have the National Institute of
Standards and Technology introducing the
secure software development framework
ssdf that is binding on a large number
of U.S federal government agencies in
terms of the software that they develop
in software that they acquire and use so
I think it's a combination of both of
those incentives or methodologies that
are coming to bear in this problem space
and what are some of the major elements
of this framework so the secure software
development framework it's pretty
far-reaching in terms of different you
know some of the things we've been
talking about like different tools that
can be applied to analysis of software
also the practices in terms of the
security of the systems on which
software is developed and released
there's you know requirements around
documentation and reproducibility of
software course so that you can know
that there's you're going to get the
same result every time and that you can
recreate software reliably so it's
pretty far-reaching and actually pretty
intimidating to your average software
developer whether that's somebody
building an application in a downstream
organization much less a you know
essentially a volunteer independent
Creator working on an open source
project in the open source Community
let's say that you implement some of
these practices and this could be having
to do with scanning or reproducibility
but you have different layers of
Automation in your pipeline and they
detect issues what kind of uh either
machine or human workflow process do you
have around evaluating can you still
ship the software is this a bug that you
can live with how do you investigate it
how do you fix it Donald
yeah so one of the practices that is I
think increasingly being recognized and
recommended in industry is as much as
possible to both standardize but also
centralize this activity within an
organization so one of the really
painful things that has happened in
recent years with the accumulation of
multiple different kinds of tools and
methodologies and all of this expertise
required around vetting the open source
software that flows into your
applications in that sense of a software
supply chain is that there's a lot for
individual developers to keep track of
right the tools that they need to become
expert in and actually there's often a
lot of repetition and kind of wasted
effort
investigating the same issues and you
know named vulnerabilities over and over
again in the context of you know
multiple applications within one
organization much less before you get to
how that repetitiveness is felt Upstream
by independent open source maintainers
maybe something that that Jordan could
talk about a little bit so one of the
approaches that we see organizations
adopting that follows the lead of some
of the most sophisticated software
development organizations in the world
like Google and Netflix and Linkedin who
have written about their practices in
this area is to centralize the vetting
of the third party open source that's
flowing into their applications do it
once within your organization to at
least save you from having you know
every developer Reinventing the wheel
for every vulnerability that emerges and
I think one of the really fascinating
opportunities is to get centralized that
body of work across organizations right
by pushing that vetting and validation
as far Upstream as possible that's one
of the places where we can actually
partner with the creators behind open
source software to address it for the
benefit of many organizations that's
going to be the most efficient way to
approach this and it also creates the
best developer experience allowing
application developers to focus on the
thing that they're trying to build not
constantly inspecting and redundantly
evaluating the building materials that
are going into it in your view Donald
then could there be a department within
a large organization or maybe for small
companies there could even be
independent
third-party quality assurance vendors
who would say things like log4j version
2.x has passed not only do they attest
they follow best practices but we've
done some external validation on them
that they didn't have input into and we
think they're good and then you could
rely on that to some degree yes very
much so so you know within organizations
we see this mandate for validating the
third party open source that's flowing
into applications becoming part of the
scope for teams that have previously
been focused on establishing a
standardized software release process or
devsecops pipeline basically the you
know standardized mechanism in these
organizations for building and releasing
software we see those teams increasingly
looking for Solutions around third party
open source vetting as part of their
mandate and I definitely believe that
there's a role for products and services
to enable those teams I mean I'm kind of
talking my own book here that's really
the area where my company tidelift is is
focused on delivering capabilities to
those centralized software release teams
around open source software and again
the the way that we are the most you
know novel a part of how we're
approaching It Is by involving the
independent open source creators who
author those projects or maintain them
in the process of validating that they
meet these standards that we all believe
are important so wrapping up this
discussion we're having now about
standards and validation something else
I wanted to cover is the idea of chain
of custody we're pulling things down
from GitHub or other other sites where
software is distributed most built
systems have a series of steps that are
building artifacts and handing them off
what are some things that can be done to
and sure that the Integrity of artifacts
at each point you're getting the thing
that you wanted to get that it hasn't
been in some way compromised I think
that once you have an artifact so for an
npm package that's a tarball for
you know a ruby gem that's the gem file
and so on once you have an artifact it's
relatively easy to
track its you know and make sure it's
not tampered with because you use some
sort of check summing mechanism and then
you pass that checksum result through a
verified Communications Channel and then
you just see if it continues to match up
the challenge is all the steps before
that artifact so you know that includes
the pull request that landed the code
that includes the repository itself the
build process to generate that artifact
and that's a little trickier
given that most languages and tooling
you know most ecosystems don't have
deterministically repeatable build
processes some do and certainly there
are attempts to build those in probably
every ecosystem but it's simply not
currently a thing that you can take a
git repository let's say and
deterministically produce an identical
artifact every time
you can get real close and you can use
heuristics so that's sort of the
challenge that I believe the salsa
project is looking at under the open ssf
and there's a lot of attempts to
kind of address that problem but I think
that personally I think that a
heuristics-based approach is the the one
that will work the best what would it
mean for for us to be identical every
time and why is that difficult I mean by
identical every time I you know I just
mean that they're like bite for bite the
artifacts are the same sometimes it's
because the time stamp the current time
is used somehow in the build process to
generate
output sometimes it's because random
numbers are used and so every time you
rerun the build process you'll get a
random variable name or some you know in
somewhere in the output when you have
those sort of points of variability
that's where you can apply heuristics to
say well this chunk of the code may
change in this type of way but the rest
of it will be identical and so you
basically extract the artifact and
compare the results you know you sort of
attempt to
you like repeat the build process and
compare and say well here's where I
expect there to be diffs and here is the
format I expect them to be you know to
differ in and so on so I think largely
those are
like there's a long list of of ways that
a build process can be non-deterministic
those are just two of the most obvious I
think it's either if you have an opinion
on the role of code signing
where you'd set up something like a pki
you can ensure that the thing you got is
from The Trusted provider that you
wanted to get it from
I think code signing is one of the
well-worn tools in this problem space
you know I mean it's not particularly
novel right so code signing you know I
can think of when we were doing code
signing when I was part of the team at
Red Hat 20 years ago or more and we
didn't invent it there I think one of
the things that's been encouraging
regarding code signing is that in a
sense it's it's become more democratized
it's more available to different kinds
of software projects so you know back in
the day and probably even today for the
sort of Linux distribution model of code
signing there's
fairly elaborate you know process and
even technology set up you know we would
have special build environment and you
know keep the signing key in a secure
Enclave you know typically some
specialized Hardware there to keep that
really locked down and so you know it
could only be applied in that special
context to you know vendor distributions
of Open Source very broadly contrast
that to today where you have some really
Innovative projects like a great example
is uh Sig store which has taken a lot of
inspiration from projects like let's
encrypt in the general web secure
communication space and applied those in
this code signing Realm by making it
easy to get a signing key to manage a
lot of the complexity around the key
verification infrastructure and the
services required there even just to
remove a lot of the the cost and
overhead of doing code signing and and
that's increasingly being adopted across
many of the open source software
ecosystems that are dominated not by
corporations with folks doing this on
staff as part of their professional
responsibilities but you know largely by
again volunteers doing this as a
contribution to the community of
technologists in these open source
ecosystems by making it you know easy
and convenient to do we can make it a
lot more pervasive and I think I see
that playing out
there's a concept I'm running into I was
researching this and it is also included
in
a part of the U.S Department of Commerce
standards for software development the
idea of a software bill of materials can
you explain what that is and what does
it have to do with supply chain Donald
sure so the idea of a software bill of
materials is basically that of an
ingredients list for your software
application it's intended to be a
comprehensive list of all of the
components that comprise your
application whether they be again
third-party open source components that
are coming from public software
repositories or whether they're coming
from commercial vendors or internally
authored right and one of the ideas of
software bills the material is that they
allow you to at least know what you're
using which is a great reference point
if you want to go and look at you know
for one thing are there known
vulnerabilities that you need to address
in the versions of software that's
flowing into your applications or a
little bit more proactively what are the
known facts or attributes what standards
do these components that are flowing
into your applications meet so that
certainly is a reasonable motivation you
know one of the things that is happened
though with the recent popularity of
software bills and material is there's a
little bit of backlash right from uh
practitioners who protest that just
having a list of the components doesn't
necessarily solve the problem right it's
a prerequisite for being able to answer
a lot of questions about your software
application what's flowing into it but
just having a list of the the packages
and the versions and so on it doesn't
make that software secure it gives you a
basis for starting the investigation or
the analysis of whether it's secure and
on what basis now if you had this list
of all the packages and versions you're
using combined with our earlier
discussion that if the projects
themselves advertise in machine readable
format some of these standards they
follow audits they've passed or you can
correlate that against a database of
known vulnerabilities it should be
possible to assemble from that a kind of
an overall profile of vulnerabilities of
the bill of materials as a whole Donald
could that be the step you need to take
Beyond just assembling the list in order
to have it be useful to you
yes so you know one useful phenomenon
that has emerged is there are
standardized formats for specifying that
list right so two of the leading
standards are cyclone DX is one in spdx
sort of an evolution of an existing
standard are standard ways to express
the software bill of materials but yet
to your point software bills and
material they're really like an index of
the things that you want to go look up
facts about right and so the next stage
of this conversation and where I see the
industry as well as regulations heading
is where is the table of facts about
those open source components that you're
looking up and that you're you know
where you're basically creating these
judgments as to the the risk profile or
the health depending on how you want to
think about it of these individual
components and how that relates to the
health of the application that you're
assembling out of these components
we're close to end of time Jordan I want
to close out with getting your thoughts
about how organizations manage the risk
of their people it's not only in
relation to supply chain that employs a
security risk and that could be through
malice or simply through errors
companies will all have adopted things
like authentication
role-based Access Control two-factor
there any processes
tooling or education that specifically
relates to securing the supply chain
through vulnerabilities of your people
one way that I would answer that
question is something that a lot of
companies have had to Grapple with
through the pandemic if you previously
tried to have a couple remote employees
and mostly in-office employees
what ended up inevitably happening was
that those remote employees would be
effectively second-class citizens of
your company
because you were designing all of your
meetings and processes around in person
and it just didn't work and so in order
to make things work equally well for
remote folks you have to design your
processes around them initially
around the least amount of physical
presence and then that also kind of
works fine for people that are in the
office or who are present
so similarly speaking
if you design all of your security
processes around the people whom you
have their social security number and
their paycheck and all of their
information and the ability to fire them
then you have not accounted for the
largest group of people that is part of
your infrastructure so I'm not saying
you shouldn't have all of those security
mechanisms of course you should but if
you design your process such that it
allows you to feel secure around people
over who you whom you have no hold and
whose identity you do not have
exhaustively detailed then you can just
be extra secure about your employees but
you will be kind of secure for the
Baseline of everyone including all of
your open source maintainers including
all of the random employees at your data
centers the janitor who's walking right
by your billion dollar server with their
mop and broom right like that person
could screw you over just as easily with
a mistake or with malice but like you
need to kind of design around all of
those sorts of things right it can also
be you can handle inclement weather
right it's all in the same bucket of
there's a lot of stuff beyond your
control and
by acknowledging that reality you can
design processes that
attempts to address that Baseline
instead of trying to artificially
restrict your mitigation I think that's
a very sound thinking but what I'm
trying to get at and maybe you've
answered this is
securing the software supply chain does
that simply mean
good security practices and there's
nothing special about supply chain you
just need to think security all the time
or these are some things different where
you really need to do this and this
practice because of supply chain that
you wouldn't necessarily care about if
you weren't thinking about supply chain
well I think the argument I'm trying to
make is that if one was applying what I
consider to be a better model of
thinking about security then the supply
chain would be no different but because
historically companies do not apply this
sort of egalitarian approach to thinking
about security the supply chain is
different in that it introduces
something that kind of a forcing
function that makes you start thinking
about and accounting for these things
okay I got I think your point and if I'm
getting it this time is that the supply
chain is one of the areas where you have
the most people who are not your
employees who are possibly impacting
your security and that is or that
broadening of thought process will then
Encompass those people did I get it this
time yes exactly right okay Donald any
closing thoughts yeah I mean I think
another way of expressing that is every
modern software development team
that you know used to be sitting in your
office perhaps and is now increasingly
distributed post-pandemic in remote
settings it also includes another ring
of humans who we haven't really
appreciated as much as we should before
those are the humans creating these open
source projects that get incorporated
into our applications and actually
usually make up most of the code in a
fully formed modern application right so
those folks have been there the whole
time there's you know more of them all
the time and we're asking more of them
and I think that the software supply
chain security conversation is forcing
folks to realize that we need to work
together collaboratively with those open
source creators to achieve the outcomes
that we desire for our internal teams
and the applications the software that
they're creating
Donald would you like to say anything
else about either tide lift or where
people can find you on the internet sure
so you know at tidelift our mission is
to help organizations tackle challenges
like this around the open source
software that they are relying on and
specifically doing so by working with
maintainers like Jordan and many others
to validate that their packages meet
some of these defined software
development practices and standards so
if you're interested in that topic area
or your organization is facing those
challenges like so many are you can find
out more at tidelift.com
t-i-d-e-l-i-f-t.com
Jordan would you like to either mention
any projects you're working on or where
people could follow you I would say the
best place is my GitHub
ljharb is my username historically I
would have also pointed you to my
Twitter but that may or may not be the
best choice as far as which projects I'm
working on I I mean I maintain hundreds
of projects so that changes hour to hour
but yeah I think the biggest thing I
would say is the amount of reach
that certain open source projects have
greatly outpaces the amount of capital
that companies are investing in having
those projects be sustainable so
everyone listening I would encourage you
to advocate for your employer to through
tide lift or through other means or both
to inject Capital into the open source
ecosystem and help us all make it a more
sustainable and secure place for the
listeners we will link to those Titleist
and LJ harb in the show notes Jordan
Harbin and Donald Fisher thank you very
much for speaking to software
engineering radio today thank you for
having us thanks so much glad to be here
for software engineering radio this has
been Robert blumen thank you for
listening
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc-radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening
[Music]